=Faithful= (Adapted from the novel "Faithful")
= مثير = (معدلة من الرواية "مثير")
= Episode 23, Chapter 12, Part 1= (The Retrial of Rulan Case)
= الحلقة 23، الفصل 12، الجزء 1 = (قضية رولان)
What happened?
ماذا حدث؟
Mr. Lou, someone is stopping us.
السيد لو، أحدهم يمنعنا
Right in the middle of the road.
في منتصف الطريق صحيح
Who is it?
من هو؟
I, Tian Xiaoling, accuse Wu Lian.
أنا، تيان شياولينغ، أتهم وو ليان
What did you say?
ماذا قلت؟
I, Tian Xiaoling, accuse Wu Lian of rape.
أنا، تيان شياولينغ يتهم وو ليان بالاغتصاب
What about you?
ماذا عنك؟
I also accuse Wu Lian.
وأنا أيضا أتهم وو ليان
I accuse Wu Lian of rape.
أنا أتهم وو ليان من الاغتصاب
Seven years ago, Lin Rulan accused Wu Lian of rape but was judged
قبل سبع سنوات، لين رولان متهم وو ليان بالاغتصاب ولكن تم الحكم عليه
to be slanderous.
تم الحكم عليه بأنه مفارقة
Today, Jueming and I both can be witnesses
اليوم، أنا وجومنغ يمكن أن نكون شهود
of Wu Lian's rape charge.
من تهمة الاغتصاب الموجهة إلى وو ليان
I hope Mr. Lou can reopen this case
آمل أن يتمكن السيد لو من إعادة فتح هذه القضية
to clear the name for Lin Rulan.
لإخلاء الاسم لين رولان
It looks like I can't leave today.
يبدو أنني لا أستطيع المغادرة اليوم
Return to the Yamen. Hold court tomorrow.
عد إلى اليمن أمسكي في الغد
Yes, turn around.
أجل، استديري
(Yanyu Tower)
(برج يانيو)
Lou Mingzhang returned to the Yamen.
عاد لو مينغتشانغ إلى يامين
The trial is scheduled for tomorrow.
ومن المقرر أن تجري المحاكمة غدا
He was about to leave the city.
كان على وشك مغادرة المدينة
But Jueming stopped him.
لكن الجميعة أوقفاه
What do you think we should do now?
ماذا رأيك يجب أن نفعل الآن؟
Jueming can't be alive.
لا يمكن للجميعة أن تكون على قيد الحياة
Without her, Lou Mingzhang would have no way.
بدوها لو مينغتشانغ لن تكون لديه طريقة
(Abandonment Letter)
(رسالة التخلي)
Master.
معلمي
What do you mean by this?
ماذا تقصد بهذا؟
I just came back from the city gate.
عدت من بوابة المدينة للتو
The news should come out quickly.
يجب أن تخرج الأخبار بسرعة
If you divorce me at this time,
إذا طرلتني في هذا الوقت
perhaps it can protect the reputation of the Xu family.
ربما يمكن أن يحمي السمعة من عائلة شو
What if I refuse?
ماذا لو رفضت؟
Back then, I insisted on marrying you as a concubine,
في ذلك الوقت، أصرت على الزواج منك كمحظية
because I intended
لأنني اعتزم
to meet Mrs. Ning.
لمقابلة السيدة نينغ
For the seven years, you have treated me well,
على مدى السنوات السبع لقد عاملتني جيدا
and your wife has treated me like a sister.
وزوجتك عاملتني كأخت
Although what I did was justified,
على الرغم من أن ما فعلته كان مبررا
I cannot be that selfish,
لا يمكن أن أكون أنانيا
making your family lose its reputation because of me.
مما يجعل عائلتك تفقد سمعتها بسببي
Do you have to go to court yourself?
هل عليك أن تذهبي إلى المحكمة بنفسك؟
I should have done this seven years ago.
كان يجب أن أفعل هذا قبل سبع سنوات
Too many people have sacrificed a lot for this.
الكثير من الناس ضحوا بالكثير من أجل هذا
How can I back down?
كيف يمكنني أن أتراجع؟
Don't you have anything you can't give up in the Xu Family?
أليس لديك أي شيء لا يمكنك التخلي عن عائلة شو؟
The seven years have been the best time of my life.
السنوات السبع الماضية كان أفضل وقت في حياتي
But you still insist on leaving.
لكنك لا تزال تصر على الرحيل
My mind is made up.
لقد اختلقت
Let me write a divorce settlement for you.
دعني أكتب تسوية طلاق لك
No, only an abandonment letter can
لا، فقط رسالة التخلي
make a clean break.
يحصل على عطلة نظيفة
(Peacefulness)
(إحلال السلام)
Wan.
انتظر
You take this with you.
أنت تأخذ هذا معك
I can't accept it.
لا يمكنني قبوله
Where do you plan to go?
إلى أين تخطط للذهاب؟
I'll stay at Huangji Embroidery House for a few days.
سأبقى في هوانغجي بيت التطريز لبضعة أيام
Madame, the carriage is waiting outside.
سيدتي، العربة في انتظار في الخارج
I will take you there.
سأوصلك إلى هناك
You don't have to. Let's part here.
لا داعي لذلك، لنترك هنا
Take care, Zhiyang.
اعتني بنفسك يا زيانغ
Take care.
اعتن بنفسك
Sir, we had a peaceful life in Hu'an.
سيدي، كان لدينا حياة سلمية في هوان
Now, we returned to Huaizhou.
الآن، عدنا إلى هواتشو
Isn't it a little impulsive?
أليس هذا مندفعة قليلا؟
After all, we don't even know who's behind this.
في النهاية، لا نعرف حتى من وراء هذا
The person who wrote to me knows about my grievances with Wu Lian,
الشخص الذي كتب لي يعرف عن مظالمهم مع وو ليان
and allows me to re-establish myself in Huaizhou Prefecture.
وتسمح لي بإعادة إنشاء نفسي في محافظة هواتشو
If I don't come back, I will feel bad.
إذا لم أعود، سأشعر بالأسف
Could it be that someone wants to use you to deal with Wu Lian?
هل يمكن أن يكون شخص ما يريد لاستخدامه للتعامل مع وو ليان؟
Back then, Wu Lian promised to connect me
إذن، وعد وو ليان أن مرتبط بي
with Mrs. Ning
مع السيدة نينغ
and help me establish myself in Huaizhou Prefecture.
لمساعدتي في إنشاء في مقاطعة هواتشو
But afterwards, he turned his back,
ولكن بعد ذلك، أعاد ظهره
threatened me with Mrs. Ning, and forced me to leave.
وهددني بالسيدة نينغ وأجبرتني على المغادرة
I must take revenge for that.
يجب أن أنتقم من ذلك
If you're right,
إذا كنت على حق
I'm willing to lend the person behind this a hand.
أنا على استعداد لإقراض الشخص وراء هذه يد
I always feel that we shouldn't get involved again.
أشعر دائما ألا ينبغي لنا التدخل مجددًا
What if we...
ماذا لو...
You're being ignorant.
أنك جاهل
Master, I found a letter at the gate.
معلمي، وجدت رسالة عند البوابة
(Meet at Tianshui Tea House tomorrow morning)
(اجتماع في دار تيانشوي تيا صباح الغد
(Huangji Embroidery House)
(بيت هوانغجي للتطريز)
Usually, no one lives in this room.
عادة، لا أحد يعيش في هذه الغرفة
You can settle down here.
يمكنك الاستقرار هنا
Thank you.
شكرًا لك
Why did you let Jueming stay in Qingshui Nunnery tonight?
لماذا تركت الجميعة يبقى في تشينغشوي ننغري الليلة؟
Wouldn't it be safer to stay here before the court session?
ألا يكون البقاء هنا أكثر أمنا قبل جلسة المحكمة؟
It's going to be a sleepless night.
ستكون ليلة خالية من النوم
Are you saying Wu Lian will target Jueming tonight?
هل تقصد أن يكون وو ليان سوف يستهدف الجميعة الليلة؟
We will find out tonight.
سنعرف الليلة
In the middle of the night, all is good.
في منتصف الليل، كل شيء جيد
(Yanyu Tower)
(برج يانيو)
Is everything alright here?
هل كل شيء على ما يرام هنا؟
Yes. What about you?
نعم ماذا عنك؟
I lost them.
لقد خسرت
I followed them out of the city.
تبعتها خارج المدينة
After that, they entered the forest.
بعد ذلك، دخلوا الغابة
It was dark, and I couldn't keep up.
كان الظلام دامسا، ولم أستطع الاستمرار
Did you notice anything suspicious outside Qingshui Nunnery?
هل لاحظت أي شيء مشبوه خارج تشينغشوي ألا نيري؟
Along my way here,
في طريقي هنا
I didn't notice anything suspicious.
لم ألاحظ أي شيء مشبوه
But it makes things stranger.
لكن هذا يجعل الأمور غريبة
I have a bad feeling. You stay, and I'll return to the city.
ينتابني شعور سيء ابقي، وسأعود إلى المدينة
Be careful.
توخ الحذر
The key is to catch the leader first.
المفتاح هو الإمساك بالقائد أولا
Meng Wan is the key among them.
منغ وان هو المفتاح بينهم
Without her, there would be nothing to fear.
بدوها لا شيء يدعو للخوف
I see. I'm on it now.
فهمت، أنا فهمت الآن
Wait a second.
انتظر
You send some people to Qingshui Nunnery.
أنت أرسلت بعض الأشخاص إلى تشينغشوي ننغري
Mr. Wu did a good trick.
قدم السيد وو خدعة جيدة
Tomorrow is the court session?
غدا هو جلسة المحكمة؟
But why did I let Jueming come back to Qingshui Nunnery tonight?
ولكن لماذا تركت الجميعة تعود إلى تشينغشوي ننغري الليلة؟
If not so, would you so confidently dare
إذا لم يكن الأمر كذلك، هل تجرؤ بثقة كبيرة
to make a move against me in the city?
لاتخاذ خطوة ضدي في المدينة؟
Don't move.
لا تتحركوا
You don't need a doctor?
ألا تحتاج إلى طبيب؟
It's not a big deal.
ليس بالأمر الجلل
How is it?
كيف الحال؟
Wu An has been detained.
وو آن قيد الاحتجاز
- Jueming... - Feng Da is bringing her back.
- الجميلة... - يجب أن... - فنغ دا ستعيدها
She should be here soon.
يجب أن تكون هنا قريبا
You have figured out
لقد عرفت
Wu Lian's real target is not Jueming.
هدف وو ليان الحقيقي ليس الجميعة
I was just speculating. I was not sure.
كنت أتكهن فقط، لم أكن متأكدا
You should have notified us in advance
كان يجب أن تخطرنا مسبقًا
to give us the idea of what's going on.
لإعطائنا فكرة عمّا يجري
I was freaked out.
لقد فزعتني
I've already informed Mr. Lou about this in advance.
لقد أبلغت السيد لو عن هذا مقدما
He dispatched a team of officers
أرسل فريقا من الضباط
and stationed them outside the house.
وتمركز بهم خارج المنزل
Once Wu Lian's people make a move,
بمجرد أن يتخذ شعب وو ليان خطوة
they can capture them on the spot.
يمكنهم الاستيلاء عليهم على الفور
With Wu An captured, Wu Lian is at his wit's end.
مع وو آن وو ليان في نهاية ذكائه
We must be cautious tomorrow.
يجب أن نتوخى الحذر غدا
Wu Lian will not easily admit his guilt.
وو ليان لن يعترف بسهولة بذنبه
Alright, go back and rest early.
حسنًا عد وارتاح في وقت مبكر
Tomorrow will be a tough battle.
غدا سيكون معركة صعبة
I've observed the night sky, and tomorrow should be a good day.
لقد شاهدت سماء الليل وغدًا يجب أن يكون يومًا صالحًا
The day is finally coming.
اليوم يقترب أخيرا
Master, there are soldiers ambushed at Huangji Embroidery House.
معلمي، هناك جنود نصب كمين في بيت هوانغجي للتطريز
Wu An has been captured.
وو آن تم القبض عليه
Alright. You may leave.
حسنًا يمكنك المغادرة
Let's go. It's time for the trial.
هيا بنا حان وقت المحاكمة
Let's watch it.
دعنا نشاهد ذلك
Yesterday, when Mr. Lou was stopped,
بالأمس، عندما تم إيقاف السيد لو
I was there.
كنت هناك
I heard
سمعت
that they were going to sue Mr. Wu.
أنهم سيقاضون السيد وو
Perhaps I heard wrong.
ربما سمعت خطأ
Sir, you're not a local, are you?
سيدي، أنت لست محليا، أليس كذلك؟
This happened seven years ago.
حدث هذا قبل سبع سنوات
Many local people still remember it.
لا يزال العديد من السكان المحليين يتذكرون ذلك
This time, it's a retrial of this case.
هذه المرة، إنها إعادة محاكمة في هذه القضية
Come on. Let's watch this.
هيا، لنشاهد هذا
Madam.
سيدتي
Madam, someone is waiting for you at home.
سيدتي، هناك من تنتظر لك في المنزل
(Benevolence)
(الولاء)
Silence. Summon Wu Lian.
صمت استدع وو ليان
Summon Wu Lian.
استدع وو ليان
(Improving People's Wellbeing)
(تحسين رفاه الناس)
Greetings, Mr. Lou.
تحياتي، السيد لو
Wu Lian, seven years ago, Lin Rulan, the embroideress of Yanyu Tower,
وو ليان، قبل سبع سنوات، لين ران مطرزة برج يانيو
accused you of rape. Do you remember that?
اتهمتك بالاغتصاب هل تتذكرين ذلك؟
Yes. Back then, Lin Rulan retracted the petition,
نعم، في ذلك الوقت تراجع لين ران عن العريضة
and admitted making false accusations.
وأقر بتوجيه اتهامات كاذبة
Whether it's a false accusation or not, it's for me to decide.
سواء كان اتهاما كاذبا أم لا إنه لي أن أقرر
But now there is a new witness.
ولكن الآن هناك شاهد جديد
So, this case needs to be reheard.
لذلك، يجب إعادة الاستماع إلى هذه القضية
Lin Rulan died seven years ago.
لين رولان مات قبل سبع سنوات
Who will file a case for this retrial?
من سيرفع قضية لإعادة المحاكمة هذه؟
According to the law,
وفقًا للقانون
they both cannot represent the deceased.
لا يمكنهما تمثيل المتوفى
Mr. Lou. Although Rulan is dead,
السيد لو، على الرغم من أن ران مات
her elder brother, Lin Lang, is alive.
أخيها الأكبر، لين لانغ، على قيد الحياة
Summon Lin Lang.
استدع لين لانغ
Mr. Lou.
السيد لو
I'm Lin Lang, Lin Rulan's elder brother.
أنا لين لانغ، الأخ الأكبر لين رولان
Today I plead with you
اليوم أناشد معك
to reopen the Rulan Case years ago
لإعادة فتح قضية ران قبل سنوات
to vindicate Rulan.
للدفاع عن رولان
(Unjust)
(ظلم)
If you claim injustice for Lin Rulan, where is your evidence?
إذا كنت تدعي الظلم على لين رولان أين دليلك؟
My sister once said
قالت أختي ذات مرة
that there were far more victims than just her.
أن هناك المزيد من الضحايا من فقط هي
I've seen all the case files.
رأيت جميع ملفات القضية
But she refused to reveal their names.
لكنها رفضت الكشف عن أسمائهم
And no one came forward to confirm her story.
ولم يقدم أحد لتأكيد قصتها
To protect those girls
لحماية هاتين الفتاتين
from being hurt again,
من التعرض للأذى مرة أخرى
Rulan chose to remain silent.
اختار رلان التزام الصمت
But what she said was not false.
لكن ما قالته لم يكن كاذبا
Today, I'm willing to stand in court
اليوم، أنا على استعداد للوقوف في المحكمة
to testify for her.
للإدلاء بشهادتها من أجلها
I entered Yanyu Tower two months earlier than Rulan.
دخلت برج يانيو قبل شهرين من رولان
I have been through everything she experienced.
لقد مررت بكل شيء التي مرت بها
Meng Wan, I remember, seven years ago, you were friends
منغ وان، أتذكر قبل سبع سنوات، كنت صديقا
with Lin Rulan.
مع لين رولان
The maids, servants,
الخادمات والخدم
and the embroideress who studied with you at the same time
والمطرقة الذي درس معك في الوقت نفسه
can testify that you two had a deep friendship.
يمكن أن يشهد أن لكما صداقة عميقة
If what you said is true,
إذا كان ما قلته صحيحا
why didn't you testify seven years ago?
لماذا لم تشهد قبل سبع سنوات؟
Or are you holding a grudge because of Lin Rulan's death,
أم أنك تحمل ضغينة بسبب وفاة لين رولان
intending to take revenge?
بنية الانتقام؟
Yes, it is deliberate revenge.
نعم، إنه انتقام متعمد
Mr. Lou, she is close to Lin Rulan.
السيد لو، إنها قريبة من لين رولان
Her testimony might not be trustworthy.
قد لا تكون شهادتها جديرة بالثقة
Amitabha. I'm Jueming.
أميتابا، أنا جنينغ
Just now, Wu Liang said
للتو، وو ليانغ قال
Ms. Meng's testimony isn't trustworthy.
شهادة السيدة مينغ ليست جديرة بالثقة
I am willing to vouch for Lin Rulan.
أنا على استعداد للإدلاء بشهادته عن لين رولان
Alright, go ahead.
حسنا، اذهبي
My real name is Tian Xiaoling. My father was a private school teacher.
اسمي الحقيقي هو تيان شياولينغ كان والدي معلمة في المدرسة الخاصة
Seven years ago, my parents found out that I loved embroidery,
قبل سبع سنوات، اكتشف والداي أنني أحبت التطريز
so they chipped in to send me to the Yanyu Tower.
لذلك غزوا لإرسالي إلى برج يانيو
Not long after that, Lin Rulan rang the drum,
لم يمض وقت طويل على ذلك لين رولان الطبل
accusing Wu Lian of rape.
يتهم وو ليان بالاغتصاب
However, I just wanted to focus on learning skills,
ومع ذلك، أردت فقط التركيز على مهارات التعلم
so I did not take it seriously.
لذلك لم آخذ الأمر على محمل الجد
I thought as long as I protected myself,
فكرت طالما أنني قمت بحماية نفسي
everything would not concern me. But I was wrong.
كل شيء لن يهمني لكنني كنت على خطأ
On the Qiqiao Festival, we had a day off.
في مهرجان تشيشياو كان لدينا يوم إجازة
When I returned from the lanterns event,
عندما عدت من حدث الفوانيس
I remembered the unfinished embroidery I left in the embroidery room,
تذكرت التطريز غير المكتمل غادرت في غرفة التطريز
so I went to fetch it alone.
لذلك ذهبت لجلبها بمفردي
Unexpectedly, I ran into Wu Lian there.
على غير المتوقع، صادفت وو ليان هناك
At first, I wasn't very cautious,
في البداية، لم أكن حذرا جدا
thinking that he didn't dare to do anything to me in the Yanyu Tower.
يعتقدون أنه لم يجرؤ على فعل أي شيء بي في برج يانيو
But I underestimated his shamelessness.
لكنني قللت من شجاعته
I thought about committing suicide,
فكرت في الانتحار
but eventually, I didn't have the courage.
ولكن في النهاية لم يكن لدي الشجاعة
So, I could only hide in the nunnery
لذلك، لم يكن بإمكاني سوى الاختباء في الرائحة
and live out the rest of my life.
وأعيش بقية حياتي
I just had a casual acquaintance with Lin Rulan.
كنت أتحدث بشكل عارض مع لين رولان
I have no reason to falsely accuse Wu Lian.
لا يوجد سبب لاتهام وو ليان زورا
I hope you can discern the truth.
آمل أن تتمكني من تمييز الحقيقة
Miss,
الآنسة
do you recognize a man named Li Chunfeng?
هل تتعرفين على رجل لي تشونغنغ؟
He was just an old friend from my childhood.
كان مجرد صديق قديم منذ طفولتي
He has nothing to do with this case.
لا شيء علاقة له بهذه القضية
An old friend? Were you two into each other?
صديق قديم؟ هل كنتما متداخل؟
Mr. Lou, Li Chunfeng is the reason she falsely accused me.
السيد لو، لي تشون فنغ هو السبب اتهمتني زورا
What do you mean?
ماذا تعني؟
Days ago, Li Chunfeng always sang at the gate of the Qingshui Nunnery,
قبل أيام، لي تشونغنغ كان دائما غنى عند بوابة تشينغشوي نونيري
expressing his sad feelings for a lady.
يعبر عن مشاعره الحزينة للسيدة
Who was he singing to?
إلى من كان يغني؟
Mr. Lou can send someone to inquire at the Qingshui Nunnery.
يمكن للسيد لو إرسال شخص ما للاستفسار في تشينغشوي نونري
Wu Lian, you've said so many things.
وو ليان، لقد قلت أشياء كثيرة
Does Li Chunfeng have anything to do with the case?
هل لي تشونغنغ لديه أي شيء علاقة بالقضية؟
Here's one more thing.
هنا شيء آخر
A few days ago, a thief broke into my house.
منذ بضعة أيام اقتحم لص منزلي
He got hurt by my servants.
تألم من قبل خدماتي
Although he managed to escape, he died from his injuries.
على الرغم من أنه تمكن من الهرب ومات من إصاباته
This thief was Li Chunfeng.
هذا اللص كان لي تشون فنغ
Well, a believer in Buddhism doesn't lie.
الشخص الذي في البوذية لا يكذب
Can you tell me if there's an affection between you and Li Chunfeng?
هل يمكنك إخباري إذا كانت هناك عاطفة بين أنت لي تشونغنغ؟
Mr. Lou, they're both seeking revenge for their friends.
السيد لو، كلاهما يسعى إلى الانتقام لأصدقائهما
and fabricating stories.
وقصص ملفّقة
If you only listen to their side of the story
إذا كنت تستمع فقط إلى جانبهم من القصة
and place the blame on me,
لإلقاء اللوم علي
I'm afraid it won't convince the public.
أخشى أن هذا لن يقنع الجمهور
You were one of those who broke my leg, right?
كنت أحد هؤلاء من كسرت ساقي، أليس كذلك؟
So what?
ماذا في ذلك؟
I couldn't understand
لم أستطع أن أفهم
why a capable person like you
لماذا شخص قادر مثلك
would always follow Wu Lian.
سوف يتبع وو ليان دائما
Then I found out you owed him a life.
إذن اكتشفت أنك مدينة له بحياة
Just for this,
فقط من أجل هذا
you did so many vicious things for him.
فعلت الكثير من الأشياء الشريرة من أجله
I don't have anything to say to you.
ليس لديّ ما أقوله لك
Your parents died early,
مات والداك باكرًا
leaving you a younger sister.
مما يدعك أخت صغيرة
Wu Lian once saved your sister's life.
وو ليان أنقذت حياة أختك ذات مرة
That's why you follow him with all your heart.
لهذا السبب تتبعينه بكل قلبك
Am I right?
هل أنا على حق؟
What does it have to do with him?
ما علاقته به؟
Have you ever thought that what you did
هل سبق لك أن فكرت
will bring karma to you and your sister?
سوف يجلب الكارما لك وأختك؟
What exactly are you trying to say?
ما الذي تحاول قوله بالضبط؟
Based on what you've done for Wu Lian,
استنادا إلى ما فعلته من أجل وو ليان
even if it's not capital offenses, but you'll be exiled.
حتى لو لم تكن جرائم يعاقب عليها بالإعدام لكنك سوف تنفي
I'm afraid you can't see your sister for the last time.
أخشى أنك لا تستطيع رؤية أختك للمرة الأخيرة
But if you can tell the truth,
ولكن إذا تمكنت من معرفة الحقيقة
Mr. Lou will deal with you leniently.
السيد لو سوف يتعامل معك بتساهل
You might still have the chance to see your sister live a happy life.
قد لا تزال لديك الفرصة رؤية أختك تعيش حياة سعيدة
I wonder what your sister would think
أتساءل ما الذي تفكر أختك به
if she knew about what you've done.
إذا كانت تعرف ما قمت به
Wu An.
وو آن
I respect you as a man.
أنا أحترمك كرجل
Now's the chance to turn back.
الآن فرصة للعودة
Can I count on you?
هل يمكنني الاعتماد عليك؟
Of course.
بالطبع
(Land Deed)
(سند الأرض)
This is the title deed. You take care of it.
هذا هو سند الملكية أنت تهتم به
Ms. Huang, why are you doing this?
السيدة هوانغ، لماذا تفعل هذا؟
Just a witness.
مجرد شهود
Even if you lose, it won't implicate our business.
حتى لو خسرت لن ينطوي الأمر على شؤوننا
Just do what I said.
فقط افعل ما قلته
If anything bad happens,
إذا حدث أي شيء سيء
you should sell this embroidery house
يجب أن تبيعي هذا المنزل التطريز
and leave here immediately with those embroideresses.
وغادري هنا على الفور مع هذه التطريز
Are you hiding something from me?
هل تخفي شيئا عني؟
Ms. Huang, we will wait for you.
السيدة هوانغ، سننتظرك
What are you doing?
ماذا تفعل؟
Mr. Zhao, I'm afraid you have to come with us to the Yamen.
السيد تشاو، أعتقد يجب أن تأتي معنا إلى اليامين
What on earth did I do wrong?
ما الذي ارتكبته بحق السماء؟
Seize him.
الاستيلاء عليه
Yes.
نعم
Take him back to the Yamen.
خذه إلى يامين
I will take people to his house.
سآخذ الناس إلى منزله
- What are you doing? - Go.
- ماذا تفعل؟ - اذهب
Sir.
سيدي
Search!
بحث!
Mr. Lou, if you reopen the old case, you must have evidence.
السيد لو، إذا أعادت فتح القضية القديمة يجب أن يكون لديك دليل
Otherwise, even if I'm a minor official,
خلاف ذلك، حتى لو كنت مسؤولا صغيرا
I have to go to the Dali Court to seek justice.
يجب أن أذهب إلى محكمة دالي لطلب العدالة
Mr. Lou, you should read it in the files.
السيد لو، يجب أن تقرأ ذلك في الملفات
In the second trial of Rulan Case,
في المحاكمة الثانية لقضية ران
there was a litigator named Zhao Yucheng.
كان هناك أحد المتقاضين اسمه تشاو يوتشنغ
I do have impressions.
لدي انطباعات
If some of you still remember
إذا كان بعضكم لا يزالون يتذكرون
the situation seven years ago,
الوضع قبل سبع سنوات
you should know
يجب أن تعرف
this litigator forged the evidence,
قام هذا المتقاضي بتقديم الأدلة
which led to Prefect Chen's judgment
مما أدى إلى حكم المحافظ تشن
that Rulan slandered Wu Lian.
أن الرلان افترضت وو ليان
And this litigator was bribed by Wu Lian.
وهذا المتقاضي تلقى رشوة من قبل وو ليان
Therefore, he deliberately bit back and reversed right and wrong.
لذلك، تراجع عمدا وانقض الصواب والخطأ
Do you have evidence?
هل لديك دليل؟
I am a witness.
أنا شهود
I'm Huang Jiaojiao, owner of the Huangji Embroidery House.
أنا هوانغ جاياوجياو صاحب بيت التطريز هوانغجي
Greetings, Mr. Lou.
تحياتي يا سيد لو
You're a witness?
أنت شاهد؟
I used to run a silk thread shop.
كنت أدير متجر خيط الحرير
One day when I was delivering goods to the Yanyu Tower,
في يوم من الأيام عندما كنت أسلّم السلع إلى برج يان يو
I saw Wu Lian's man leading a person
رأيت رجل وو ليان يقود شخصا
into the study.
في الدراسة
The next day I saw this person in court.
في اليوم التالي رأيت هذا الشخص في المحكمة
It was Lin Rulan's litigator.
كانت متقاضي لين رولان
Why didn't you speak out in court?
لماذا لم تتحدث في المحكمة؟
I was in a difficult situation.
كنت في وضع صعب
The Yanyu Tower was my big customer.
كان برج يان يو زبوني الكبير
I can only protect myself first.
لا يسعني إلا أن أحمي نفسي أولا
Now Huangji Embroidery House has grown,
الآن، لقد نما بيت هوانغجي للتطريز
while my Yanyu Tower has collapsed.
بينما انهار برج يي يو الخاص بي
You're probably the biggest beneficiary.
ربما أنت أكبر مستفيد
I have to say you have ulterior motives.
يجب أن أقول إن لديك دوافع خفية
Huai Embroidery has replaced Yanyu Embroidery,
هواي إمبراطور حل محل يانيو الإمبراطور
becoming one of the birthday gifts for Her Majesty.
أن يصبح أحد هدايا عيد الميلاد لصاحبة الجلالة
Yanyu Embroidery has lost.
لقد فقد يان يو التطريز
Wu Lian.
وو لان
Is what she said true?
هل ما قلته صحيح؟
Indeed, I met Mr. Zhao before the trial.
بالفعل، قابلت السيد تشاو قبل المحاكمة
But I didn't bribe him.
لكنني لم أرشحه
Instead, I wanted him to persuade Lin Rulan
بدلًا من ذلك، أردته لإقناع لين رولان
not to make a mistake.
عدم ارتكاب خطأ
If I remember correctly,
إذا كنت أذكر على نحو صحيح
the laws do not prohibit meeting with a litigator.
القوانين لا تمنع الاجتماع مع أحد الخصوم
So, let's listen
لذلك، دعنا نستمع
to what Mr. Zhao says. Bring him here.
إلى ما يقوله السيد تشاو أحضره إلى هنا
What was your deal with Wu Lian
ما هو اتفاقك مع وو ليان
during the Rulan Case seven years ago?
خلال قضية رولان قبل سبع سنوات؟
Just now, Wu Lian admitted
للتو، اعترف وو ليان
that he met with you privately.
أنه التقى بك على انفراد
If you lie, I won't let you go.
إذا كذبت، لن أتخلى عنك
I did meet with Wu Lian.
اجتمعت مع وو ليان
Was it just a meeting?
هل كان مجرد اجتماع؟
Wu Lian wanted me to lose the case.
وو لان يريدني أن أفقد القضية
He promised to help me establish a foothold.
وعد لمساعدتي في إنشاء موطئ قدم
You are such a treacherous person.
أنت شخص غبي
What exactly did you do?
ماذا فعلت بالضبط؟
He asked me to switch the handkerchief left by Ding Ru prior to her death.
طلب مني تغيير المنديل تركه دينغ رو قبل وفاتها
So, Lin Rulan was accused of fabricating evidence.
لذلك، تم اتهام لين ران باختلاق أدلة
Wu Lian, how do you explain this?
وو ليان، كيف تفسر هذا؟
This man is Meng Wan's cousin.
هذا الرجل هو ابن عم منغ وان
Why is he coming forward to testify at this point?
لماذا يتقدم للإدلاء بشهادته في هذه المرحلة؟
Moreover, there's no evidence.
علاوة على ذلك، لا يوجد دليل
The evidence is here.
الدليل هنا
I discovered it in Mr. Zhao's house.
اكتشفت ذلك في منزل السيد تشاو
It should be Ding Ru's handkerchief.
يجب أن يكون مندي دينغ رو
I have caught Zhao Yucheng's concubine
لقد قبضت على محظية تشاو يويتشنغ
to testify.
للإدلاء بشهادته
Bring her here.
أحضرها إلى هنا
What exactly happened when Zhao Yucheng acted
ما الذي حدث بالضبط عندما تصرف تشاو يوتشنغ
as Lin Rulan's litigator seven years ago?
كمقاوم لين رولان قبل سبع سنوات؟
Speak up.
قل بصراحة
At that time, I was his personal maid.
في ذلك الوقت، كنت أخته الشخصية
When he just arrived at Huaizhou,
عندما وصل للتو إلى هواتشو
Wu Lian sent someone to find him.
أرسل وو ليان شخصا للعثور عليه
They figured out Lin Rulan would ask him for help, so...
اكتشفوا كان رولان يطلب منه المساعدة، لذا...
Keep going.
استمروا
I do not know details, but that handkerchief...
لا أعرف التفاصيل لكن ذلك منديل...
I had someone embroider an exact copy
كان لدي شخص ما مطرقة نسخة دقيقة
and handed it to Master.
وسلمته إلى المعلم
Zhao Yucheng secretly replaced the evidence.
تشاو يوتشنغ سرا حل محل الأدلة
How can you prove that it was under my command?
كيف يمكنك إثبات ذلك أنه كان تحت قيادتي؟
Mr. Wu, you don't give up, do you?
السيد وو، أنت لا تستسلم، أليس كذلك؟
How can you deny it before the evidence and witness statements?
كيف يمكنك إنكار ذلك قبل الأدلة وإفادات الشهود؟
Mr. Lou, a man broke into Huangji last night
السيد لو، اقتحم رجل إلى هوانغجي الليلة الماضية
and intended to kill me.
بنية قتلني
You should already know about this.
يجب أن تعرف بالفعل عن هذا
Why don't you interrogate this man now?
لماذا لا تستجوب هذا الرجل الآن؟
There may be more evidence coming.
قد يكون هناك المزيد من الأدلة قادم
Bring the person here.
أحضر الشخص إلى هنا
Wu Lian, do you recognize him?
وو ليان، هل تتعرف عليه؟
Of course, I do.
بالطبع، أجل
His name is Wu An, the top steward of the Yanyu Tower.
اسمه وو آن الضابط الأول في برج يانيو
Correct?
صحيح؟
Wu An does work in the Yanyu Tower.
وو آن يعمل في برج يانيو
But he is not a slave, so he is free in my house.
لكنه ليس عبدا لذلك هو مجاني في منزلي
You may ask him what he has done.
يمكنك أن تسأله ماذا فعل
Tell me. Who gave you the orders?
أخبرني، من أعطاك الأوامر؟
Mr. Lou, I beg you to save an innocent woman.
السيد لو، أتوسل إليك لإنقاذ امرأة بريئة
What do you mean by that?
ماذا تقصد بذلك؟
Meng Wan found out that I liked her maid.
اكتشفت منغ وان أنني أُعجبت بأختها
To threaten me,
لتهديدي
she hid her in a secret place.
خبأتها في مكان سري
Her life or death is unknown,
حياتها أو موتها غير معروفة
And the lame man
والرجل الغامض
just went to the prison
ذهب فقط إلى السجن
to threaten me with the life of the maid,
لتهديد بي بحياة الآنسة مو
forcing me to frame Mr. Wu.
تجبرني على تأطير السيد وو
It's a setup, truly heinous!
إنه تصميم، شنيع حقا!
Yes.
نعم
It is intolerable!
إنه لا يمكن تحمله!
It's personal grudge between me and Meng Wan.
إنها ضغينة شخصية بيني وبين منغ وان
I like her maid,
أحب أختها
so Meng Wan kept tormenting her.
لذا واصلت منغ وان تعذيبها
I've been holding a grudge.
لقد كنت أحمل ضغينة
Wu An, you made a big mistake.
وو آن، لقد ارتكبت خطأ كبيرا
I only regret that I couldn't kill her last night.
أنا نأسف فقط لأنني لم أستطع قتلها ليلة أمس
So, you two planned it long ago.
لذلك، أنتما خطة لذلك منذ فترة طويلة
Meng Wan, get mad at me.
منغ وان، أغضب مني
Do not hurt the innocent.
لا تؤذي الأبرياء
Mr. Lou.
السيد لو
Meng Wan wants to avenge Lin Rulan.
منغ وان يريد الانتقام من لين ران
Tian Xiaoling wants to avenge Li Chunfeng,
تيان شياولينغ يريد للانتقام من لي تشونغنغ
and Zhao Yucheng is a liar.
و تشاو يوتشنغ هو كاذب
What can they prove?
ماذا يمكنها أن تثبت؟
Exactly. What can they prove?
بالضبط، ماذا يمكنها أن تثبت؟
I have evidence.
لدي دليل
Submit it.
أرسله
Please look, Mr. Lou.
يرجى إلقاء نظرة يا سيد لو
What's she doing?
ماذا تفعل؟
This plum blossom on my back is evidence.
زهر البرقوق هذا على ظهري دليل
Those who know Wu Lian will understand.
أولئك الذين يعلمون أن وو ليان سوف يفهمون
The plum blossoms he embroiders are unique.
أزهار البرقوق هو إمبراطور فريد من نوعه
Somebody, get plum blossoms embroidery from Yanyu Tower.
شخص ما، الحصول على التطريز في أزهار البرقوق من برج يانيو
I have a handkerchief.
لدي منديل
Mr. Wu embroidered it himself.
السيد وو مطرز به بنفسه
They are indeed identical.
وهما متشابهان بالفعل
Mr. Wu did it.
السيد وو فعل ذلك
Is that true?
هل هذا صحيح؟
It's really him.
إنه هو حقًا
I'm fine.
أنا بخير
Seven years ago, the night I met him,
قبل سبع سنوات، في الليلة التي التقيت به فيها
I wanted to leave quickly.
أردت المغادرة بسرعة
But he seemed to have had a drink in a good mood,
لكن يبدو أنه كان يشرب في مزاج جيد
so he started talking embroidery with me.
لذلك بدأ يتحدث التطريز معي
When I said a falling plum blossom seemed desolated,
عندما قلت زهر البرقوق الآخذ في السقوط بدا مهلكا
and a plum blossom on the tree showed more dignity,
وزهر البرقوق على الشجرة أظهر المزيد من الكرامة
it provoked his anger.
لقد أثار غضبه
In his fury, he pinned me to the embroidery table.
في غضبه، ركز عليّ إلى طاولة التطريز
But that wasn't enough for him.
لكن ذلك لم يكن كافيا بالنسبة له
At that time, I was out of my senses,
في ذلك الوقت، كنت خارج رشدي
filled with despair, like the living dead.
مليء باليأس مثل القتلى الأحياء
He took a needle and embroidered this plum blossom
أخذ إبرة وتطرّق إلى زهر هذا البرقوق
on my shoulder stitch by stitch,
على خنزير كتفي بواسطة خنزير
trying to leave this plum blossom on me for a lifetime.
تحاول ترك زهر البرقوق هذا علي مدى الحياة
Wu Lian.
وو ليان
What else can you argue about?
ما الذي يمكنك الجدل بشأنه أيضا؟
I have long heard that no one in Huaizhou
لقد سمعت لفترة طويلة أنه لا أحد في هواتشو
can imitate your embroidery skills.
يمكن تقليد مهاراتك التطريزية
Listen to me, Mr. Lou.
استمعي إلي يا سيد لو
That day, the two of us were discussing embroidery.
في ذلك اليوم، ونحن الاثنان كنا نناقش التطريز
But she not only disobeyed, but also talked back.
لكنها لم تعصي فقط بل أيضا تحدثت
I just gave her a punishment.
أعطيتها عقابا فحسب
Our bodies are given by our parents.
أجسامنا يصدرها والدانا
How could you hurt her body?
كيف يمكن أن تؤذي جسدها؟
Yes, how could you?
نعم، كيف أمكنك ذلك؟
Fortunately, Yanyu Tower has been burned.
لحسن الحظ، برج يانيو تم حرقه
Such an evil person.
مثل هذا الشخص الشرير
How can this woman get married in the future with a scar on her body?
كيف يمكن لهذه المرأة أن تتزوج في المستقبل مع ندبة على جسدها؟
Yes, how could you do this?
نعم، كيف أمكنك فعل هذا؟
Mr. Lou, today these two women
السيد لو، هاتان السيدتان اليوم
accuse me of rape.
اتهمتهما بالاغتصاب
Even if my punishment method is controversial,
حتى لو كانت طريقة العقاب الخاصة بي مثيرة للجدل
it can't prove that I raped them.
لا يمكن أن يثبت أنني اغتصبتهن
If you use an embroidered plum blossom to determine my crime,
إذا استخدمت زهر برقوق مطرزة لتحديد جريمتي
I am afraid that it is too far-fetched.
أخشى أنه بعيد جدا
Everyone, I have seen many familiar faces here today.
الجميع، لقد رأيت العديد من الوجوه المألوفة هنا اليوم
I want to ask you all a question.
أريد أن أطرح عليكما سؤالا
How have you been over the past seven years?
كيف كنت على مدى السنوات السبع الماضية؟
Seven years ago, Rulan told me
قبل سبع سنوات، قال لي روان
to forget all this and start anew.
أن أنسى كل هذا وأبدأ من جديد
I don't know how you've been over these years,
لا أعرف كيف كنت على مدى هذه السنوات
but I dream of my days in the Yanyu Tower every day.
لكنني أحلم بيومي في برج يانيو كل يوم
I dare not forget for a moment.
لا أجرؤ على النسيان للحظة
We are the victims.
نحن الضحايا
But are we the only victims these years?
لكن هل نحن الضحايا الوحيدات هذه السنوات؟
How many young ladies walked
كم من السيدات الشابات سار
into Yanyu Tower with hopes
إلى برج يانيو بآمال
but left in desperate?
ولكن هل بقي في يأس؟
Yet, Wu Lian, who's to blame,
ومع ذلك، وو ليان، من يتحمل اللوم
continues to be teach embroidery.
لا يزال يقوم بتعليم التطريز
Where is justice in this world?
أين العدالة في هذا العالم؟
Rulan,
روان
Jueming, and me.
وجمينغ وأنا
Perhaps many of you
ربما الكثيرون منكم
may think we're overreaching ourselves.
قد يظن أننا نتجاوز أنفسنا
But I know behind me are all of you
لكنني أعرف خلفي جميعكم
and many victims like us.
والكثير من الضحايا مثلنا
Even if one person is weak,
حتى لو كان شخص واحد ضعيفا
what about ten, a hundred, or a thousand people?
ماذا عن عشرة مائة أو ألف شخص؟
A woman is inherently difficult.
المرأة صعبة بطبيعتها
It's even harder to reveal the painful past.
الأمر أصعب للكشف عن الماضي المؤلم
I was once like all of you,
كنت مثلكم جميعا مرة
thinking about hiding in a corner where no one can see,
أفكر في الاختباء في زاوية حيث لا يمكن لأحد أن يرى
because I fear rumors and judgments.
لأنني أخشى الشائعات والأحكام
And I fear the damage to the reputations of my family.
وأخشى الضرر على سمعة عائلتي
I even thought about ending my life.
حتى أنني فكرت في إنهاء حياتي
But then, what did we do wrong?
لكن إذن، ماذا فعلنا الخطأ؟
Why do we, as victims,
لماذا نحن كضحايا
have to carefully hide our pains
علينا أن نخفي آلامنا بعناية
and live with nightmares,
للعيش مع الكابوس
yet not even have the courage to speak the truth?
ولكن ليس لديهم حتى الشجاعة للحديث عن الحقيقة؟
The one who did evil is this man.
الشخص الذي فعل الشر هو هذا الرجل
So today, I am pleading you to step up
لذلك اليوم، أناشد منك أن تساعده
not for others, but for ourselves,
ليس للآخرين، بل لأنفسنا
so that no nightmares will follow us.
حتى لا يتابعنا أي كابوس
Stop avoiding it.
لا تتجنبوا ذلك
Mr. Lou, I have a request.
السيد لو، لدي طلب
Go ahead.
هيا
May I ask for a white screen to be placed outside the Yamen?
هل يمكنني أن أطلب شاشة بيضاء ليتم وضعها خارج اليامين؟
Why?
لماذا؟
The embroideresses got married and had children.
تزوجت المطرزات وكان لديهم أطفال
Once they speak the truth, it may destroy
بمجرد أن يتحدثوا الحقيقة قد يدمر
their hard-earned peaceful lives.
حياتهم السلمية التي اكتسبوها بجهد
If they were allowed to write the truth
إذا سمح لهم بكتابة الحقيقة
on the white screen anonymously,
على الشاشة البيضاء دون الكشف عن هويتهم
perhaps it could allay their concerns.
ربما يمكن أن يبدد شواغلهم
Mr. Lou.
السيد لو
No, this is an unprecedented request.
لا هذا طلب غير مسبوق
I cannot agree.
لا أستطيع الموافقة
Dismiss!
انتهي!
Get out of here.
اخرج من هنا
You two come with me.
أنتما الاثنان معي
After all these years, you're still so naive.
بعد كل هذه السنوات ما زلت ساذجا جدًا
Nobody will admit it.
لن يعترف أحد بذلك
Perhaps he is right.
ربما هو على حق
Seven years have passed, but nothing changed now.
لقد مرت سبع سنوات لكن لم يتغير شيء الآن
Maybe it won't change in the future either.
ربما لن يتغير هذا في المستقبل أيضا
♪Withered orchids are falling♪
♪ أوركيد مطر ينهار ♪
♪In a misty rain♪
♪ في مطر رهيب ♪
♪I've been traveling♪
♪ لقد كنت مسافرين ♪
♪Across the country♪
♪ عبر البلاد ♪
♪I'm as sad as you♪
♪ أنا حزينة بنفس القدر ♪
♪Walking through high-rises♪
♪ المرور عبر الارتفاعات العالية ♪
♪Sobbing desperately into my hands♪
♪ تمسكا بيدي بشدة ♪
♪The candle is on♪
♪ الشمعة في الجوار ♪
♪Even if I can't return♪
حتى لو لم أستطع العودة ♪
♪I have no regrets♪
♪ ليس لدي أي ندم ♪
♪The wind is blowing♪
♪ الرياح تهب ♪
♪Snow is falling♪
♪ الثلج يهبط ♪
♪I'm fearless♪
♪ أنا بلا خوف ♪
♪And move on in any case♪
♪ وتواصل العمل في أي حال ♪
♪I follow my passions♪
♪ أتابع عواطفي ♪
♪Looking back♪
♪ نظرة إلى الوراء ♪
♪I bring back a flood of memories♪
♪ إنني أعيد فيضان من الذكريات ♪
♪I've been through a lot♪
♪ لقد مررت بالكثير ♪
♪It is unforgettable♪
♪ إنه لا يُنسى ♪
♪Dawn arrives♪
♪ وصل الغضب ♪
♪Walking through high-rises♪
♪ المرور عبر الارتفاعات العالية ♪
♪Sobbing desperately into my hands♪
♪ تمسكا بيدي بشدة ♪
♪The candle is on♪
♪ الشمعة في الجوار ♪
♪Even if I can't return♪
حتى لو لم أستطع العودة ♪
♪I have no regrets♪
♪ ليس لدي أي ندم ♪
♪The wind is blowing♪
♪ الرياح تهب ♪
♪Snow is falling♪
♪ الثلج يهبط ♪
♪I'm fearless♪
♪ أنا بلا خوف ♪
♪And move on in any case♪
♪ وتواصل العمل في أي حال ♪
♪I follow my passions♪
♪ أتابع عواطفي ♪
♪Looking back♪
♪ نظرة إلى الوراء ♪
♪I bring back a flood of memories♪
♪ إنني أعيد فيضان من الذكريات ♪
♪I've been through a lot♪
♪ لقد مررت بالكثير ♪
♪It is unforgettable♪
♪ إنه لا يُنسى ♪
♪Dawn arrives♪
♪ وصولها ♪